Guide to the Dudley Nichols Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dudley Nichols papers
1903-1969
YCAL MSS 671
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.92
(7 boxes)
The Dudley Nichols papers contain correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the life and work of American screenwriter and director Dudley Nichols. Correspondence with family, friends, authors, critics, actors, and directors includes a number of authors who, like Nichols, served in the Armed Forces during World War I or resided or worked at least briefly in California and Hollywood. There are letters from Edward Dahlberg, William Faulkner, Gene Fowler, Aldous Huxley, William Marsh, Christopher Morley, Henry Miller, Ernst Toller, and Thornton Wilder, as well as Charlie Chaplin and Jean Renoir. Work by Nichols dating from 1920 to the late 1950s includes several scripts for cinematic and theatrical productions and shorter works, including poetry, reviews, and essays. Personal papers feature Nichols's military records dating from his service in the U.S. Navy and photographs.
Nichols, Dudley, 1895-1960
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift from various sources, 1949-1987.
The bulk of the collection, including incoming letters, outgoing letters to family, most writings, and all personal papers, was received by gift from Dudley Nichols, 1949-1960, and his widow, Esta Nichols, 1961-1966. Additional materials, including outgoing letters to others and some writings, were acquired by gift from other sources, 1960-1987.
For more information consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Dudley Nichols Correspondence Regarding the Screen Adaptation of Eugene O'Neill's Mourning Becomes Electra. Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Dudley Nichols (1895-1960)
Dudley Nichols, a screenwriter and director, was born in Wapakoneta, Ohio to Grant Byron Nichols and Mary Means. Nichols developed a fascination with electricity and worked on a crew that repaired high-tension power lines and as a ship's radio operator on the Great Lakes. In 1915 he entered the University of Michigan, where he studied electrical engineering and was employed as a student assistant in charge of the radio laboratory. At the outbreak of World War I, Nichols enlisted in the Navy and set up a school for radio operators. Later, he was part of the North Sea Mine Laying Force.
After the armistice Nichols volunteered for minesweeping duty and invented a method of electrical protection for minesweepers for which he received the Distinguished Service Medal in 1920. Following the war Nichols worked as a reporter for ten years for the Philadelphia Evening Public Ledger, then the New York Evening Post, and finally the New York World. During this period he also studied at New York University and sailed again as a radio operator.
In 1929 Nichols was persuaded by Winfield Sheehan, head of Fox Studios, to become a screenwriter. His first film, Men Without Women (1930), directed by John Ford, led to a collaboration with Ford that lasted until 1947 and resulted in fourteen films, including The Lost Patrol (1934), The Informer (1935), Stagecoach (1939), The Long Voyage Home (1940), and The Fugitive (1947). During the 1940's Nichols also worked with Fritz Lang, Jean Renoir, Howard Hawks, Leo McCarey, René Clair, and Elia Kazan. He wrote the final script of Ernest Hemingway's For Whom the Bell Tolls (1943) and produced and directed two films based on his own scripts, Sister Kenny (1946) and an adaptation of Eugene O'Neill's Mourning Becomes Electra (1947).
Biographical information taken from "Dudley Nichols." Dictionary of American Biography. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1980. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 13 Dec. 2012.
Scope and Contents
The Dudley Nichols papers contain correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the life and work of American screenwriter and director Dudley Nichols. Correspondence with family, friends, authors, critics, actors, and film directors includes a number of authors who, like Nichols, served in the Armed Forces during World War I or resided or worked at least briefly in California and Hollywood. There are letters from Edward Dahlberg, William Faulkner, Gene Fowler, Aldus Huxley, William Marsh, Christopher Morley, Henry Miller, Ernst Toller, and Thornton Wilder, as well as Charlie Chaplin and Jean Renoir. Work by Nichols dating from 1920 to the late 1950s includes several scripts for cinematic and theatrical productions and shorter work, including poetry, reviews, and essays. Personal papers feature Nichols's military records dating from his service in the the U.S. Navy and photographs.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1915-1960. II. Writings, 1920-1958. III. Personal Papers, 1903-1969.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Motion picture producers and directors -- United States; Screenwriters -- United States -- 20th Century -- Archives; Film scripts; Photographic prints; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Motion picture producers and directors -- United States -- 20th Century; Screenwriters -- United States -- 20th Century; Chaplin, Charlie, 1889-1977; Dahlberg, Edward, 1900-1977; Faulkner, William, 1897-1962; Fowler, Gene, 1890-1960; Huxley, Aldous, 1894-1963; Marsh, W. Lockwood (William Lockwood), 1886-1963; Morley, Christopher, 1890-1957; Nichols, Dudley, 1895-1960; Renoir, Jean, 1894-1979; Toller, Ernst, 1893-1939; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975
- Correspondence, 1915-1960; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries for Incoming, Outgoing, and Third-Party correspondence. Arranged alphabetically within subseries by last name of correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. contains correspondence with family, friends, authors, critics, actors, and film directors. Correspondents include a number of authors who also served in the Armed Forces during World War I or resided or worked at least briefly in California and Hollywood. There are letters from Edward Dahlberg, William Faulkner, Gene Fowler, Aldus Huxley, William Marsh, Christopher Morley, Henry Miller, Ernst Toller, and Thornton Wilder. There is also correspondence with film figures Charlie Chaplin and Jean Renoir.
  - Incoming
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Dudley Nichols, 1949-1960.
    - Atkinson, Brooks, undated (Box 1)
    - Behrman, S. N. (Samuel Nathaniel), 1953, 1955 (Box 1)
      Includes letter from Berhman to "Irving"
    - Belasco, David, 1928 March (Box 1)
    - Benoit-Lévy, Jean, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
    - Brooks, Van Wyke, 1953-1956 (Box 1)
    - Chaplin, Charlie, 1947 May 27 (Box 1)
    - Cinémathèque française, 1955 March 8 (Box 1)
    - Commins, Saxe, 1957 April 11 (Box 1)
    - Crowther, Bosley, 1957 September 4 (Box 1)
    - Dahlberg, Edward, 1952-1953 (Box 1)
    - Daniels, Guy, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - Effinger, John, 1921 June 7 (Box 1)
    - Ernst, Morris L., 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - Faulkner, William, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - Feuchtwanger, Lion, 1952, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Fowler, Gene, 1954-1958, undatedf (Box 1)
    - Gassner, John, 1945-1954 (Box 1)
    - Huxley, Aldous, 1944 November 27 (Box 1)
    - Kenny, Elizabeth, 1944 May 1 (Box 1)
    - Lardner, Ring, 1925 October 28 (Box 1)
    - Lefevre, Edwin, 1926 December 6 (Box 1)
    - March, William, 1952 (Box 1)
    - Masters, Dexter, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - Masters, Edgar Lee, 1939-1945, undated (Box 1)
      Includes drafts of writings by Masters and letter from Alice Davis
    - Miller, Henry, 1943, undated (Box 1)
    - Morley, Christopher, 1924-1949, undated (Box 1)
      Includes letter from Rollo Ogden to Morley and printed ephemera
    - The Nation, 1927 January 24 (Box 1)
    - Nichols, Grant B. (father), 1933-1935, undated (Box 1)
    - Nichols, Kitty (mother), 1935, undated (Box 1)
    - Paulson, Arvid, 1952-1960 (Box 1)
    - Philip, Sister Mary, 1945-1960, undated; 2 (Box 2)
      Includes drafts of writings
    - Stokowski, Leopold, 1944 (Box 2)
    - Swope, Herbert Bayard, 1925-1955 (Box 2)
      Includes letters to Swope from others
    - Tesla, N[ikola?], 1921 July 11 (Box 2)
    - Toller, Ernst, 1937 July 37 (Box 2)
    - Tully, Jim, 1939-1941 (Box 2)
      Includes printed version of "The Wabash Cannon Ball" by Tully
    - Webster, Samuel, 1949-1959 (Box 2)
    - Wilder, Thornton, 1952 August 18 (Box 2)
    - Young, Art, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Unsorted correspondence, 1921-1951, undated (Box 2)
  - Outgoing
    Acquired from various sources, 1960-1981. For more information consult the appropriate curator.
    - Babb, James T., 1957 (Box 2)
      Includes carbons of letters from Babb to Nichols
    - Brown, Nils F., 1952-1957, undated (Box 2)
    - Effinger, John R., 1921 July [6?] (Box 2)
    - Elder, Arthur, 1922-1923, undated (Box 2)
    - Elder, David, undated (Box 2)
    - Feuchtwanger, Leon, 1953-1957 (Box 2)
    - Fowler, Gene, 1954, undated (Box 2)
    - Gassner, John, [1949?]-1959 (Box 2)
    - Henri, Florette, 1956 December 16 (Box 2)
    - Hoffman, Irving, 1956-1959, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    - Merrild, Knud; Merrild, Else, 1937-1957, undated (Box 3)
    - Nichols, Grant B., 1915-1923; 5 (Box 3)
      Includes enclosures
    - Nichols, Grant B., 1925-1927, undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - [Nichols], John, 1917 July 10 (Box 4)
    - Nichols, Lucille, 1917 May 13 (Box 4)
    - Orlovitz, Gil, undated (Box 4)
      Contains photostats
    - Paulson, Arvid, 1954-1959 (Box 4)
    - Philip, Sister Mary, 1944-1959, undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - Renoir, Jean; Renoir, Dido, 1949-1959, undated (Box 4)
      Includes copies
  - Third-Party Correspondence
    - Burness, Peter to Gustave O. Arlit, 1956 April 20 (Box 4)
      Includes enclosure
    - [Nichols], Esta to "Mac", undated (Box 4)
- Writings, 1920-1958; Series II; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Series II. contains work by Nichols dating from 1920 to the late 1950s. The series contains several scripts for cinematic and theatrical productions and shorter work, including poetry, reviews, and essays.
  - "Come Angel Band," script, typescript, and playbill, 1936, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - "Dialogue on a Rainy Day," draft, tyypescript, and printed version, 1958, undated (Box 4)
  - "Double Alex," script, typescript, 1949 April 29 (Box 5)
  - "Epitaph for a Father," script, typescript and typescript carbon, undated; 3 (Box 5)
  - "Exiles," review, typescript, undated (Box 5)
  - "The Father," script, typescript, and printed ephemera, 1934-1935 (Box 5)
  - "A Few Characters in Search of a Novel," typescript, undated (Box 5)
  - "Gentlemen, Be Seated," review, typescript carbon, undated (Box 5)
  - "House in the Sky," script, typescript carbon, 1939 December 11 (Box 5)
  - The Informer, radioscript, undated; 2 (Box 5)
  - Judge Priest, shooting script, mimeograph, 1934 April 27 (Box 6)
  - The Long Voyage Home, screenplay, undated (Box 6)
  - [Poems], 1920-1957, undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - "Secret Places of the Groin," review, printed version, The Nation, 1955 November 5 (Box 6)
  - "Sin is Abolished," drafts, typescript, undated (Box 6)
  - "Witches Win in York," printed version, The Nation, 1929 January 23 (Box 6)
  - Unsorted writings, 1927-1947, undated; 3 (Box 6)
- Personal Papers, 1903-1969; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series III. Personal Papers features Nichols's military records dating chiefly from his service in the the U.S. Navy during World War I and photographs.
  - Clippings, 1925-1928, undated (Box 7)
  - Military records and material, 1913-1939, undated; 3 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous unsorted material, 1905-1969, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - Photographs, 1903-1941, undated (Box 7)
    Includes photographs of Nichols, Robinson Jeffers, Aldus Huxley, and others